<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Of perjury a sermon preach'd at the assizes held at Chester, April the 4th, 1682 / by John Allen, M.A. Fellow of Trinity College in Cambridge ...</title>
            <author>Allen, John, M.A., Fellow of Trinity College in Cambridge.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 65 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A23640</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A1034</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8027</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12381222</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12381222</idno>
            <idno type="VID">60755</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A23640)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60755)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 267:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Of perjury a sermon preach'd at the assizes held at Chester, April the 4th, 1682 / by John Allen, M.A. Fellow of Trinity College in Cambridge ...</title>
                  <author>Allen, John, M.A., Fellow of Trinity College in Cambridge.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Benj. Tooke ... and George Atkinson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Perjury --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:60755:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60755:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>OF PERJURY. A SERMON Preach'd at the ASSIZES HELD AT CHESTER, <hi>April</hi> the 4<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> 1682.</p>
            <p>By <hi>John Allen,</hi> M. A. Fellow of <hi>Trinity</hi> College in <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> and Chaplain to the Lord Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Totius injuſtitiae nulla capitalior eſt, quam eorum, qui tùm, cùm maximè fallunt, id agunt, ut viri boni eſſe videantur.
<bibl>
                  <hi>Tully de Offic. Lib. 1.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Benj. Tooke</hi> at the <hi>Ship</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, and <hi>George Atkinſon,</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Cheſter.</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:60755:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60755:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFUL Sir <hi>Robert Leyceſter</hi> Baronet, <hi>Foreman;</hi> AND The reſt of the Worthy and Loyal Gentlemen of the <hi>Grand Jury,</hi> for the Aſſizes lately held at <hi>Cheſter.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe Preaching of this Sermon was undertaken at the requeſt of the High Sheriff, an Honeſt, True-hearted and Loyal Gentleman, an Ancient and Faithful Servant to His Majeſty: But the Printing of it was extorted by Your importunity; You have thruſt me into the World perfectly againſt my humour and inclination; and You have thereby expos'd me to the exceptions and cenſures of this captious Age, of peeviſh, ill-natur'd, and ill-affected Perſons: To You therefore I flee for ſhelter; Your Protection I claim, on Your judgements I have relyed: You are bound in Honour and Juſtice to excuſe the Faults of this Diſcourſe; to vindicate the Truths, to juſtifie the Doctrine, and to abhor the Perjuries herein mention'd.</p>
            <p>I have ſome encouragement to hope, that the Sermon will pleaſe the honeſt, the Faithful and the Loyal, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:60755:3"/>it pleaſes you, who are eminently ſuch; that it may be in ſome degree uſeful and ſeaſonable for theſe Times, becauſe You think ſo: And if it chance to be carp't and cavell'd at by the Factious and the Seditious; by falſe Witneſſes, and corrupt Jurors, by the Old Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanters, or New Aſſociators, as being peculiarly levell'd againſt their Deſigns and Practiſes; Yet however we need not fear, we have this advantage upon them, that whoever rail, or even mutter againſt us, do thereby confeſs their own guilt; and ſo their Credit is crack't, and their Teſtimony becomes invalid; Their Tongues are no Slander, their ill-words are no Diſparagement; no more, than their good ones can be a Commendation.</p>
            <p>My Deſign in Preaching, and Yours in Publiſhing this Diſcourſe, I dare confidently ſay, were both the ſame; To Convince the Guilty, and make them truly ſenſible of their Sin and Danger, in order to their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance: And to fix and 'ſtabliſh the ſlippery and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering Tempers of thoſe, who are apt to be drawn in by great Examples, or specious Pretences, or the Proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of temporal Advantages.</p>
            <p>That our joynt Endeavours may prove, by God's bleſsing, uſeful and inſtrumental to theſe great and good Ends, ſhall be the hearty Prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your moſt Obedient, and moſt Humble Servant</hi> John Allen.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:60755:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Of Perjury,</hi> A SERMON Preach'd at the ASSIZES HELD AT CHESTER. <hi>April</hi> the 4<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> 1682.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Leviticus XIX. 12.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>And ye ſhall not ſwear by my Name falſly.—</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I Have made choice of theſe words, as a ſubject both ſuitable to this ſolemn <hi>Occaſion</hi> and ſeaſonable for the <hi>Times:</hi> The times are notoriouſly peſter'd, diſturb'd and endanger'd by the variety and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quency of <hi>Perjury;</hi> and upon <hi>this</hi> account the <hi>Occaſion</hi> may ſeem to require a ſerious and plain Diſcourſe, that, by God's bleſſing, may prove ſerviceable, and uſeful,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:60755:4"/>to adviſe and admoniſh All that are concern'd, ſo to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge their duty to <hi>God,</hi> to their <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Country,</hi> that not the leaſt blemiſh or tincture of this ſin may defile their Conſciences, or diſparage their proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</p>
            <p>I had intended to have giv'n an account (by way of Preface) of the <hi>Nature, Kinds, End</hi> or <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſefulneſs, Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs</hi> and <hi>Obligation</hi> of <hi>Oaths,</hi> together with the moſt uſual <hi>Forms</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies</hi> of ſolemn Swearing, Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and Modern; but am forc'd to wave all that, by reaſon of the largeneſs and copiouſneſs of my ſubject. My deſign is to diſcourſe of the ſin of Perjury, and to give you a full account of it in this method.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I ſhall ſhew what Perjury is, and how many ways it is committed.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The heinouſneſs and aggravations of it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. What are the uſual occaſions of, inducements and temptations to this ſin.</p>
            <p n="4">4, And laſtly. The puniſhments of it by the Laws of God and Man.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Perjury (as the Text tells us) is a Swearing by God's Name falſly: as <hi>Philo</hi> deſcribes it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a calling God to witneſs for the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of a Lye: And is committed theſe ſeveral ways.</p>
            <p n="1">1. When Men do aſſert and teſtifie upon Oath, a thing to be <hi>true,</hi> which they know to be <hi>falſe;</hi> when they ſwear, That they ſaw, or heard ſuch or ſuch things done or ſpoken, which their own Conſciences tell 'em, they did not.</p>
            <p n="2">2. When Men do aſſert and teſtifie upon Oath, a thing to be true, of the truth of which they are not fully aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured: Nay though the thing ſhould be true; yet being it is more then they knew, they are however guilty of <hi>Perjury;</hi> becauſe they call God to witneſs, and appeal
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:60755:4"/>to him for the atteſtation of that as certainly true, which, for ought they know, may be utterly falſe.</p>
            <p>To theſe we may add, that when Men declare upon Oath, <hi>this</hi> or <hi>that</hi> to be their judgment, and the ſenſe of their minds, which really is not ſo; or which is grounded on bare ſuſpicions or fond wiſhes; or which proceeds not from full conviction, but from partial and by-reſpects, This is alſo Perjury.</p>
            <p>So then, if Witneſſes ſworn to teſtifie the <hi>Truth,</hi> the <hi>whole Truth,</hi> and <hi>nothing but the Truth,</hi> do depoſe falſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, do conceal, and ſuppreſs, the moſt material Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; do improve and enlarge their teſtimony with the additions of their own fancies, and inventions, They are plainly perjur'd.</p>
            <p>So likewiſe, when Men ſworn to enquire, and inform the Courts of Juſtice, do not <hi>find Bills</hi> according to fair, full and legal Evidence, againſt ſome ſorts of perſons, out of love, fear, favour and affection, or hope of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward: Or do find 'em againſt others, out of envy, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, malice, &amp;c. If Men, from the fore-named mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, do acquit the Guilty, or condemn the Innocent: This is Perjury in the Jurors, in God's account, in his ſight, according to <hi>his</hi> Laws, though poſſibly the Laws of the Realm may take no Cognizance, or hold of them.</p>
            <p>Theſe things I mention, and deſire All, that are, or may be concern'd, to conſider ſeriouſly, and to be ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of their danger; and that, becauſe ſuch miſcarri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages do happen ſometimes to the ſcandal of Religion, to the reproach of our Nation, to the obſtruction of Juſtice, and the perverſion of our good Laws: And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Mens paſſions, and prejudices, and intereſts do ſo frequently tincture their judgments, and biaſs their wills, that it is a very hard thing for ſome Men to be <hi>Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> and not be <hi>Parties</hi> too; they are inſenſibly, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:60755:5"/>yet powerfully ſuborn'd, to give in their Evidence, with more or leſs weight, according to their inclination or averſion to a perſon, to a Party, or a Cauſe: And it is not to be deny'd, that <hi>Jurors</hi> alſo may be in danger to abuſe their truſt and aſſume a liberty to admit or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject what they pleaſe of the Evidence; to believe what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is depos'd in ſome caſes, and in others juſt nothing at all: Nay to interpret the Laws in favour of the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders, and declare it againſt Law, to put the Laws in execution.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They that promiſe upon Oath, what they intend not to perform; or are unreſolv'd and indifferent, whether they ſhall perform it, or not; Theſe are <hi>ipſo facto</hi> guilty of <hi>Perjury:</hi> becauſe they ſwear by God's Name falſly; they call God to witneſs, and to vouch for the truth, and ſincerity of their promiſe, when the intention of their minds does not concur with the words of their mouths: Now although it be the Prerogative of the ſearcher of hearts, to know Mens thoughts; yet, in ſome caſes, it is not impoſſible, no nor difficult for <hi>us,</hi> to paſs a right judgment upon ſome Mens very intentions; we may <hi>know them by their fruits,</hi> their words, and their actions, do abundantly expoſe and diſcover the treachery of their minds: It is not ſo eaſily <hi>forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten,</hi> as it was <hi>forgiven,</hi> that a <hi>Rebellion</hi> was begun by Men, who at the ſame time promis'd, and ſwore, and <hi>Covenanted</hi> to <hi>preſerve</hi> and <hi>defend</hi> the <hi>King's perſon,</hi> and <hi>Authority:</hi> And if we obſerve now (as who can chooſe?) the <hi>Behaviour,</hi> the <hi>Diſcourſes,</hi> the <hi>Practiſes</hi> of thoſe yet remaining, and <hi>Surviving Politicians,</hi> and of their too forward <hi>Pupils</hi> alſo; we ſhall find it an hard task to judge favourably of them, and to reconcile their <hi>ſuſpicious carriage,</hi> with their <hi>Loyal Oaths.</hi> And we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but take notice, that ſeveral Men for their advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, or in order to conceal, as yet, their Trayterous,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:60755:5"/>and Unripe deſigns, will not refuſe any Teſt, or Oath requir'd by the Law, to expreſs, and make a ſhew of their Loyalty; though God and their own Souls can witneſs, and their actions declare, that they had much rather let them alone, and don't intend to be obliged by them: Men that will come to the <hi>Sacrament</hi> once or twice in their lifes, in a <hi>Civil way,</hi> that is, upon en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring on ſome Office, ſome gainful or honourable em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, but ſcarce ever come near the Church, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther before or after: And will take the Oaths of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance,</hi> and <hi>Supremacy,</hi> rather than forgo any temporal advantage, or be diſabled for ſervice; but make no Conſcience to break 'em, when 'tis more for their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt.</p>
            <p n="4">4. They alſo are guilty of <hi>Perjury,</hi> that having pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd upon Oath ſincerely, and with an honeſt inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, do yet afterwards <hi>fall off,</hi> and <hi>renounce the obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> do not faithfully, and reſolvedly endeavour, and take care to <hi>fullfill their word,</hi> do <hi>act contrary</hi> to their Oath, when a juſt occaſion requires, and calls for the performance of their promiſe, or ſworn duty. I uſe <hi>all theſe</hi> expreſſions, that I may reach to moſt or All caſes of this nature: And this is call'd properly <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (ſays <hi>Chryſippus</hi> the Philoſopher) that is, to ſwear falſly,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ap. Stob.</hi> c. 28.</note> ſo as that our <hi>actions</hi> do not anſwer to our <hi>words,</hi> as the former was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, when our <hi>words</hi> do not agree with our <hi>hearts</hi> and <hi>minds:</hi> And accordingly he tells us, that at the inſtant of taking (or rather giving) a promiſſory Oath, a Man cannot be ſaid properly, either <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, becauſe, as it reſpects the future, a Man cannot be known to have ſworn truly, or falſly, till the time of fullfilling his promiſe does diſcover his faithfulneſs, or falſhood: But this Critical nicety will not hold: for if a Man having confirm'd his promiſe by an Oath, and that ſincerely, and with intention to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:60755:6"/>keep it (for inſtance, to pay a ſum of Money upon a ſet day) ſhall in the intermediate time contrive to evade the obligation, and to break his word, you cannot but think, that he is really guilty of Perjury; and that too, though he ſhould not be able effectually to ſhirk, and avoid the payment at the appointed time. But how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever there can be no diſpute, no uſe of this diſtinction, as to the breach of thoſe promiſſory Oaths, that are ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to <hi>re-inforce</hi> a known, and <hi>antecedent duty;</hi> or thoſe, whoſe obligation does take place, and lay hold upon our Conſciences, <hi>at,</hi> and <hi>from</hi> the <hi>very moment</hi> of ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring: For they that do not continue in that honeſt, and faithful intention, in which they took their Oaths; they that have no mind to be oblig'd any longer by them, are contriving how to break them to the beſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, are ſeeking excuſes, and evaſions to palliate their perfidiouſneſs: Theſe Men are guilty of Perjury, nay though (for want of opportunity and power) they proceed no further; becauſe having <hi>bound their Souls with a bond,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 30.2.</note> having ſworn by the <hi>help of God,</hi> and by the <hi>Contents</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> to perform their promiſe, having call'd in God to be Surety for them, and (as it were) bound with them; They do yet, as much, as in them lyes, as far as they dare for fear of the Laws, and Civil puniſhments, without any reſpect, or regard to Conſcience, and the fear of God, diſengage themſelves from the obligation of their Oaths.</p>
            <p n="5">5. They are involv'd in the guilt of Perjury, who againſt, or without the conſent of the Supreme Power, do frame, and impoſe upon others, or take themſelves <hi>new</hi> Oaths, contrary to, and deſtructive of their former obligations. This is a tickliſh point, as the times go, and therefore I ſhall explain and confirm it the more largely and carefully. I muſt tell you then, that an Oath can re-inforce a former; or induce a new obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:60755:6"/>where there was none before; but cannot deſtroy an antecedent one; or ſuper-induce another repugnant to it; and one main reaſon hereof is this, becauſe by every ſuch obligation, a <hi>right</hi> does accrue to another; to <hi>Him,</hi> to whom the promiſe is made; and we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come thereby indebted to Him, and bound in Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; and He hath a Right and Lawful power to chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge, and demand of us, as a duty, the juſt performance of it: and therefore it is moſt unreaſonable, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equal, moſt injurious and unjuſt, that <hi>his right</hi> ſhould be infring'd by any <hi>act</hi> of ours, without his <hi>leave</hi> and <hi>releaſe</hi> firſt obtain'd.</p>
            <p>I muſt further tell you, that we are bound in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to be ſubject to all our <hi>Superiours</hi> according to the nature, quality and extent of their dominion over us: And conſequently to the <hi>Supreme</hi> or <hi>Soveraign</hi> in all things, not counter-manded by <hi>His</hi> only <hi>Superiour</hi> the <hi>King</hi> of Heaven; which duty and obligation of ours, a ſubſequent Oath taken <hi>againſt</hi> or <hi>without</hi> his conſent, can by no means diſannul and cancel. All which is prov'd from <hi>Numb.</hi> 30. at the beginning of the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, where the Rule is thus given: If a Daughter ſtill remaining <hi>in her Fathers Houſe;</hi> or if a Wife do <hi>vow a vow</hi> unto the Lord; if the <hi>Father</hi> or <hi>Husband</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively do <hi>hear</hi> of it, and <hi>hold his peace,</hi> and expreſs no diſlike of it, the Vow <hi>ſhall ſtand;</hi> but if <hi>Father</hi> or <hi>Husband</hi> do upon notice thereof <hi>diſallow</hi> it, then the Vow of either of them ſhall not ſtand, ſhall be <hi>of none effect:</hi> God will <hi>forgive</hi> and excuſe them, but the obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhall not take place: And if this be ſo, then certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by parity of reaſon, we may conclude, That no <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject</hi> hath a right or power to oblige himſelf by Oath, to the <hi>Prejudice,</hi> and againſt the <hi>Conſent</hi> of the <hi>Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign:</hi> And if any Man hath been drawn in, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled in ſuch ſnares, He <hi>muſt</hi> forthwith diſengage
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:60755:7"/>himſelf, and come off, begging <hi>God</hi>'s and the <hi>King</hi>'s par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for his folly and raſhneſs; He muſt remember that he is <hi>pre-engag'd;</hi> He may, and ought to renounce the treacherous Oath, as being illegal, and unable to lay hold on his Conſcience.</p>
            <p>But this is not all; if the <hi>Matter</hi> of theſe Oaths be unlawful, if againſt our plain duty, and our former Oaths and Obligations; then do they certainly involve us in Perjury; and cannot be juſtified, neither by the <hi>goodneſs</hi> of the <hi>intention,</hi> nor the <hi>greatneſs</hi> of <hi>ſome Mens fears,</hi> nor the <hi>piety</hi> of their <hi>pretences,</hi> nor their <hi>Zeal</hi> for <hi>Religion</hi> and the <hi>publick good:</hi> Such are the Solemn <hi>Leagues</hi> and <hi>Covenants, Engagements</hi> and <hi>Aſſociations,</hi> contriv'd by perfidious <hi>Politicians,</hi> and greedily ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by the <hi>Seditious</hi> and the <hi>Schiſmatick,</hi> by the <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of Change,</hi> the <hi>Male-contents,</hi> the blind and furious <hi>Zelots,</hi> and the <hi>deluded</hi> and <hi>ill-taught party</hi> of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p n="6">6, And laſtly, They are guilty of <hi>Perjury,</hi> who make uſe of <hi>Tricks</hi> and <hi>Cheats,</hi> and <hi>ſubtle Artifices,</hi> to evade and elude the obligation of their Oaths; who will not underſtand the words of an Oath, in their <hi>Aſſertions,</hi> or <hi>Promiſes,</hi> according to the plain, genuin, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon acception of them, but by faſtning a <hi>ſecret</hi> Senſe of their own, upon ſome <hi>Ambiguous</hi> terms, or by ſome <hi>Reſerves,</hi> or <hi>Exceptions,</hi> or <hi>Additions</hi> within their minds, do quite alter the meaning of the words, and thereby intend neither to be oblig'd to ſpeak truth, nor perform their promiſes.</p>
            <p>The Romiſh Caſuiſts are notoriouſly faulty in this point, they are not aſham'd to preſcribe Rules of <hi>Aequivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, Mental Evaſion,</hi> and <hi>Reſervation;</hi> they ſet down Forms, and propoſe ſeveral Modells, and Examples of them, for the help of <hi>Novices:</hi> they teach their Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, <hi>when</hi> and <hi>where,</hi> and upon what <hi>occaſions</hi> they may
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:60755:7"/>be uſed; and undertake to prove, that they are lawful and expedient, and in ſome caſes neceſſary: And their forward Scholars do eaſily learn, and are very expert and ready to practiſe according to their inſtructions.</p>
            <p>But perhaps <hi>They</hi> are not the only <hi>Aequivocators</hi> in the World; they don't engroſs the whole Trade to themſelves: There are <hi>ſome True Proteſtants</hi> towardly enough to imitate the ſubtleties of the <hi>Jeſuit;</hi> who, when they find they are <hi>cramp't</hi> and <hi>fetter'd</hi> by an Oath, that does <hi>pinch</hi> and <hi>fret</hi> 'em, then have recourſe to <hi>Jeſuitical</hi> diſtinctions, to their ſhifts, <hi>Reſerves</hi> and <hi>Evaſions;</hi> they ſwear firſt, and then <hi>after vows</hi> they <hi>make enquiry:</hi> they will find or make ſome creeping hole to eſcape at; they will <hi>skrew</hi> and <hi>wreſt</hi> and <hi>wind</hi> and <hi>turn</hi> and <hi>torture</hi> the words, till they have made 'em pliant, and yielding to their Senſe, and conſiſtent with their <hi>Deſigns:</hi> They take no care to perform, what they have ſworn, but only to for-ſwear themſelves <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geniouſly,</hi> and according to <hi>Art.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But none of theſe tricks will exempt <hi>either ſort</hi> of 'em from the guilt of this ſin; and that, becauſe an Oath ought to be taken, and kept too, in the moſt <hi>plain, free, open-hearted</hi> and <hi>ingenuous</hi> way that can be, with all <hi>ſimplicity</hi> and <hi>ſincerity</hi> of mind; and in <hi>that</hi> Senſe of the words, that they <hi>uſually</hi> bear, and are <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly</hi> taken in; and particularly in <hi>that</hi> Senſe, that the <hi>Parties</hi> to whom we ſwear, they for whoſe <hi>ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> or <hi>information</hi> we give our <hi>promiſe</hi> or <hi>teſtimony,</hi> do, or muſt be ſuppos'd to <hi>underſtand</hi> 'em in.</p>
            <p>I will diſpatch this particular with this neceſſary Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation; That there may be <hi>Aequivocation</hi> in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>frame</hi> of an Oath, as well as in the minds of deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Swearers: Some Oaths both of <hi>former</hi> and <hi>later</hi> date, are ſo neatly contriv'd, ſo cunningly worded, and ſo doubtfully expreſs'd; are adorn'd and ſet forth in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:60755:8"/>ſuch ſpecious colours; are compos'd and recommended by ſuch <hi>Zelous Reformers;</hi> are guilded over with ſuch glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious pretences, that many eaſie, and well-meaning peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are drawn in,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.11.</note> 
               <hi>in their ſimplicity,</hi> and <hi>know not any thing</hi> of the main Deſign, and the Rebellion intended. But when they are once catch't, then ſhall they be taught, that theirs is a <hi>Sacred</hi> Oath; that they muſt make a Conſcience of <hi>this,</hi> more then <hi>all</hi> their former obligations; then ſhall they be taught to underſtand the words in a <hi>larger,</hi> or quite <hi>different</hi> Senſe; and ſo by degrees ſhall at laſt come to think, that they are bound in Conſcience, and by virtue of their Oath, to <hi>deſtroy</hi> the Prince, whom they promis'd to <hi>preſerve;</hi> to <hi>ruine</hi> the Religion, which, to the beſt of their thinking, they ſwore to <hi>maintain;</hi> and to commit thoſe outrages, that Murder, and Sacriledge, and Rapine, which they never dream't of, or could perceive in their Religious <hi>Covenant;</hi> but would poſſibly have abhorr'd the very remote apprehenſions of ſuch horrid villanies. That's the Firſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Second is the Heinouſneſs of this ſin of <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury;</hi> and <hi>that</hi> will appear in general: Firſt, if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that there is no ſin almoſt whatever ſo <hi>odious,</hi> and <hi>infamous</hi> in the judgment of All Mankind, that have any ſenſe of <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>common honeſty,</hi> as <hi>This:</hi> For the <hi>Reverence</hi> of an Oath is <hi>Natural</hi> to us, and implan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in us; this Sacred, and Solemn Appeal to God, hath been ever held in ſo great Veneration, both as a part of divine and immediate worſhip, and as the main ſupport of truth, and faithfulneſs; that, whoever did preſume to violate and profane it, was generally abhorr'd, as a moſt impious and treacherous Villain: Methinks it makes ones ſtomach <hi>riſe</hi> againſt him; a Man can't ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe or pitty him, can't find in his heart to pray for him, or wiſh him well.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:60755:8"/>
            <p>Give me leave, therefore, to expoſe this <hi>great Sin</hi> in its proper <hi>Colours,</hi> and load it with its due <hi>aggravati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;</hi> that ſo All thoſe, that have ſeen, how many ways it can be committed, may by a juſt ſenſe of its horrour and heinouſneſs, be admoniſh'd, and terrify'd from in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volving themſelves in ſo great guilt.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, Perjury is an Affront to God, and to All thoſe glorious Attributes, that ſhine forth, and diſplay themſelves in the Government of the World. He that <hi>forſwears</hi> himſelf, does thereby profane the moſt Holy, and Reverend Name of God, by making it the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his deceit, and treachery: He appeals to the <hi>Searcher</hi> of <hi>Hearts</hi> to conceal and countenance his <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie:</hi> He calls upon the God of Truth to atteſt a Falſhood: He dares his Power, and defies his Juſtice and Vengeance: He lays his unclean <hi>Hand</hi> upon the <hi>Holy Goſpels;</hi> He <hi>kiſſes</hi> the <hi>Book</hi> with his deceitful and lying Lips: He invokes the <hi>help</hi> of <hi>God</hi> to protect and proſper his <hi>Perjury:</hi> He renounces All the <hi>Truths:</hi> He diſclaims all the <hi>Promiſes:</hi> He diſregards all the <hi>Curſes</hi> contain'd in that Holy Volume.</p>
            <p>Other ſorts of Sinners are generally more modeſt, and ſhame-fac't; uſe more reſpect and good manners to their <hi>Maker,</hi> even when They offend Him: They have commonly an awe, and concern upon them, and ſtrive (though in vain) to conceal themſelves from his All<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeing eye, and to cover their ſins with ſecreſie, or dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; or at leaſt to put off the thoughts of God's pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and ſtifle the fears of his Power and Juſtice: But the Perjurer is rude and inſolent, is loud and clamorous;
<q>
                  <l>—Aſpice quantâ</l>
                  <l>Voce neget, quae ſit ficti conſtantia vultûs.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Juvenal. Sat.</hi> 13.</note>
                  </l>
               </q> He has cas'd his countenance with Impudence and Hypocriſie: He fears neither God nor Man: He ſwears
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:60755:9"/>with courage, and a <hi>loud</hi> Voice: He ſtares God in the Face: He calls upon Him to look on, to hearken and be a Witneſs, how cunningly and ſecurely He can abuſe and profane His Name for the Confirmation of a lye; He challenges God to come forth and engage, and be bound with him, for what He never intends, or will take no care to perform.</p>
            <p>Can there be a ſin more impudent and heinous than <hi>This?</hi> Is it poſſible to reconcile this with ſo much as the ſhew, and pretence of Religion? Can thoſe Men that affront their God, and profane his Name at this rate, perſwade themſelves, or any Body elſe, that they have any the loweſt degree of <hi>Love,</hi> or <hi>Fear,</hi> or <hi>Truſt</hi> in God, or <hi>any</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtian graces?</hi> Is it poſſible for thoſe Men,
<note place="margin">Epiſt. 154. <hi>ſine ullâ dubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatione, minus malum eſt per Deum falſum jurare veraci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, quam per Doum verum fallacitèr.</hi>
               </note> for <hi>All</hi> their pretences, and noiſe, to be heartily <hi>Zelous</hi> againſt <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Idolatry,</hi> who make no ſcruple of <hi>Perjury?</hi> It is not, if S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> tells us true; <hi>That without all doubt, it is a leſs ſin to ſwear truly by a falſe God, than to ſwear falſly by the True One.</hi> And ſo makes <hi>Perjury</hi> a more heinous Crime, than <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry</hi> it ſelf.</p>
            <p>And is it not a madneſs in us to cry up, and magnifie, and take <hi>Thoſe</hi> for our <hi>Examples</hi> and <hi>Leaders,</hi> and the <hi>Guides</hi> of our Conſciences, and Practices, that have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſworn themſelves over and over; that were never <hi>true</hi> to <hi>any</hi> Government; that never were, or never will be faithful to <hi>This.</hi> Oh my Soul! come not thou into their ſecrets; Have thou nothing to do with thoſe wicked Men, that will never be oblig'd to ſpeak truth, or perform their promiſes.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Perjury is not only an impious and impudent af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front to <hi>God;</hi> but is alſo moſt injurious and miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous to 1. <hi>Man,</hi> to our Neighbour: And that firſt in his private capacity, in <hi>All</hi> his concerns of what kind ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, though never ſo dear unto him: His Life, his
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:60755:9"/>Liberty, his Reputation, his Eſtate are All at the mercy of the Perjurers:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 35.11.</note> and though They <hi>lay to his charge things, that He knows not,</hi> as <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks; though They invent and forge groundleſs accuſations, againſt the moſt perfect Innocence; yet if they prove and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt 'em upon Oath, if they call on God to confirm their lying Evidence, There is uſually no ſence, no ſhelter againſt their malice and treachery.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Themiſt. Orat.</hi> 1.</note> We can guard our ſelves, in moſt caſes, againſt open violence: We can preſerve our Goods from <hi>Thieves</hi> and <hi>Robbers:</hi> We may find, generally, ſome guard and ſhelter againſt other injuries; but Perjury is an <hi>Arrow that flieth in darkneſs;</hi> it is a <hi>Surpriſe,</hi> a <hi>Stabb:</hi> It deſtroys us by <hi>Mining</hi> or <hi>Ambuſcade;</hi> it <hi>takes away</hi> all our <hi>Armour,</hi> the <hi>Armour</hi> of <hi>Innocence,</hi> in <hi>which</hi> we <hi>truſted:</hi> It cuts off our <hi>retreat,</hi> it leaves us naked, and unable to ſtand, and defend our ſelves againſt its <hi>ſecret</hi> violence.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Perjury is injurious to Converſation, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce: All our Dealings, and Trade, and Contracts, and Friendſhips are grounded upon, and managed by the <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Aſſurance,</hi> that we <hi>give</hi> and <hi>take</hi> of the ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of our minds, and purpoſes, expreſs'd by our words, and in great concerns, confirm'd by our Oaths: This tyes and compacts us together, makes us uſeful, and helpful, and ſerviceable to each other: This creates, and preſerves Love and Kindneſs, and Mutual Affection, and Endearments, and the <hi>Intercourſe,</hi> and <hi>Circulation</hi> of good turns and benefits. But if after <hi>all this,</hi> Men ſhall aſſume a liberty to deceive and impoſe upon their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondents, to deny their own words, and to break their promiſes: What muſt <hi>This</hi> come to? How ſhall any Man know, whom to truſt, whom to employ, or whom to ſpeak to? If this ſhould prevail, all <hi>Society</hi> muſt be <hi>diſſolv'd;</hi> every Man muſt ſet up for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:60755:10"/>and fall into Mr. <hi>Hobbs's ſtate of Nature,</hi> and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim War againſt all Mankind beſide.</p>
            <p n="3">3. But then further: As to Government, and the Conſequents of it, Peace, and Order, and juſt Liberty: There is nothing but Perjury can deſtroy <hi>it,</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive us of <hi>them:</hi> Nothing but Perjury can carry on Faction, and begin a Rebellion: Nothing but the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Profanation of God's Name, can ruine the Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy. All that are entruſted in any Office or Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, either <hi>Civil, Military,</hi> or <hi>Sacred,</hi> have given the beſt aſſurance to the <hi>Prince,</hi> that a Promiſe can make, and an Oath can bind; that <hi>They will bear Faith, and true Allegiance to His Majeſty, His Heirs, and Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, and Him and Them will defend, to the uttermoſt of their power, againſt All conſpiracies and attempts whatſoever, that ſhall be made againſt His, or Their Perſons, their Crown and Dignity,</hi> &amp;c. But if Theſe <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Bonds</hi> muſt be broken in ſunder upon every <hi>Sham,</hi> and hold us no longer, than <hi>ſome Men</hi> pleaſe; then cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly do we incur the guilt of a moſt heinous and grievous ſin, or rather a maſs and heap of horrid Crimes: We not only violate the Laws of God and Man, but alſo become moſt treacherous and ungrateful to the <hi>Prince,</hi> that <hi>relies</hi> and <hi>depends</hi> upon our <hi>fidelity,</hi> that hath oblig'd us All by the general <hi>influences</hi> of his moſt gracious and benign Government; and many of the moſt <hi>Factious</hi> and <hi>dangerous tempers</hi> among us, with particular, ſignal and <hi>undeſerved</hi> favours.</p>
            <p>If we break our Faith, and renounce our Oaths, then we know, what muſt be the <hi>Conſequence</hi> and <hi>Effects</hi> of the <hi>Perjury:</hi> We ſhall have new Oaths, <hi>Iron ſhackles,</hi> clap't upon our Conſciences: <hi>Wars</hi> and <hi>Confuſions, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition</hi> and <hi>Rebellion;</hi> and (if theſe proſper) then the Ruine of the <hi>Monarchy,</hi> and of the <hi>Church,</hi> the <hi>Slavery</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:60755:10"/>of our <hi>Country; Tyranny</hi> and <hi>Arbitrary</hi> power exercis'd upon us by the <hi>worst</hi> of our <hi>fellow Subjects;</hi> This ſhall be our <hi>Portion,</hi> and the due reward of our <hi>Perfidiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. And Laſtly, Perjury is injurious to <hi>publick iuſtice:</hi> For ſince an <hi>Oath</hi> is the main ground of All proceedings, in order to decide Controverſies, is the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, The greateſt aſſurance, that a Man <hi>can</hi> give of the truth of his <hi>Teſtimony;</hi> the <hi>laſt reſult,</hi> the higheſt and utmoſt <hi>appeal</hi> that we <hi>can</hi> make; and is the <hi>end of all ſtrife,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.16.</note> as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſpeaks: Since Oaths are of conſtant uſe in Judiciary Cauſes, whether <hi>Criminal</hi> or <hi>Civil,</hi> and the beſt means to find out the truth of <hi>Matter</hi> of <hi>Fact,</hi> to determin of <hi>Right</hi> and <hi>Wrong,</hi> to give every Man his due, to clear the Innocent, and diſcover the Guilty: It is plain then, that Perjury utterly defeats all theſe great and uſeful ends, and makes the <hi>Law</hi> it ſelf, the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of injuſtice. Perjury in the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> miſguides, and miſ-leads the <hi>Court,</hi> deſtroys Mens rights, counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and confirms the wrongful claims, and pretenſions of <hi>Knaves</hi> and <hi>Forgers,</hi> and lays on groundleſs accuſations on the moſt honeſt, and innocent: And Perjury in the <hi>Jury</hi> can fetch off, and reſcue the moſt dangerous Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minals from fair and legal <hi>Tryals;</hi> or acquit the guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in ſpite of Evidence. So that if this impudent and miſchievous ſin, ſhould obtain ſtill for the <hi>future,</hi> as it hath done for ſome <hi>late years;</hi> ſhould gain ground univerſally, as it hath in ſome <hi>particular places;</hi> our Laws would be clearly inſignificant, or rather baſely perverted: the juſtice of the Nation obſtructed; the innocent deſtroy'd; and the worſt of Men protected, and encourag'd: Our <hi>Terms,</hi> and our <hi>Courts</hi> might be adjourn'd to the great Day of Judgment; and the <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers</hi> become as uſeleſs and <hi>contemptible</hi> as the <hi>Clergy.</hi> That's the Second</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:60755:11"/>3. I proceeed to the Third, to enquire, what are the <hi>occaſions</hi> of, or <hi>temptations</hi> to this ſin: And this point is ſet properly in this place; that if we look back to the laſt general, and conſider what a great and heinous ſin This is, and look forward to the fourth Head; and obſerve, what are the <hi>puniſhments</hi> denounc't againſt it, by the Laws of God and Man; we may with juſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon be induc't, and perſwaded to reject the temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and cut off the occaſions of it. And indeed it is ſadly ſtrange, and a matter of wonder, and horrour, that Men profeſſing Religion with ſo much Zeal and noiſe, that ſo many Scrupulous, Preciſe, and True Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, falſly ſo call'd, ſhould make ſo light, ſo little or nothing of this great and heavy ſin, ſhould ſwallow Perjuries without ſtrain or chewing; ſhould have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to 'em, frequently, and upon all occaſions, as to their Guard and Caſtle, as to their <hi>Artillery</hi> and Arms of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive and defenſive. It is not preſumable, that Men of any honeſty or Religion, would make ſo bold with God, and be ſo miſchievous to Mankind, and human Society, as I have ſhewn theſe falſe-ſwearers are: And I am confident, that Perjury to a Conſcience truly <hi>ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> would appear ghaſtly and frightful; it is not for a <hi>Novice</hi> to pretend to this Helliſh accompliſhment: A Man muſt be moulded and modell'd by previous qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lification, and diſpoſitions, or perverted and debauch't with erroneous and corrupt Principles; or at leaſt driv'n and hurried on by powerful examples, or violent paſſions, or importunate luſts, before he can arrive to this height of impudence and villany.</p>
            <p>It need not coſt us much trouble or time, to enquire how, and whence it comes to paſs, that ſo many do venture upon this dreadful ſin; for if you conſider how many ſeveral ways Perjury is committed, and take notice alſo of thoſe, that are ſcandalouſly guilty of it;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:60755:11"/>I dare aſſure; that you will clearly perceive it to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from ſome one or more of theſe following parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Atheiſm:</hi> A denying of God and Providence: This indeed were a plauſible and rational account <hi>of,</hi> a good plea, and excuſe <hi>for</hi> Perjury, if <hi>Atheiſm</hi> it ſelf were rational: An <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> ſhould he ſwear falſly eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hour, upon every occaſion, would do like an <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſt,</hi> and act conſiſtently to his Principles: For what ſhould hinder him from complying with our Forms, and Cuſtoms of calling God to witneſs, when it is for his advantage? He knows of no God to come at his call, to look on, and be a Witneſs of his words, and the ſearcher of his heart: He believes no Judgment to come, no future ſtate: The unquenchable Fire, the never-dying Worm are Dreams and Fables, and the inventions of <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Politicians</hi> to keep the <hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> in awe, according to <hi>His</hi> wiſe opinion: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he is ever ready to ſwear, and lye, and promiſe forward and backward: He makes no ſcruple to take or break any Oath, becauſe he has no Conſcience, no fear of a <hi>Deity,</hi> and conſequently, can ſecurely throw off any obligation: And the truth is, if a Man were to ſet up the Trade of Perjury, and make his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes by it; The readieſt way were to begin with Atheiſm; if he could once conquer that, the other would be an eaſie and profitable employment, and require no ſtock, but <hi>that</hi> of impudence and inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And in that other ſort of Perjury, the Trade of Treachery, and Unfaithfulneſs, and by the help of <hi>That,</hi> ſetting up for <hi>Faction,</hi> and cutting out work for <hi>Rebellion:</hi> It is eaſie to obſerve, That the moſt <hi>Atheiſtical</hi> perſons are commonly the chief contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:60755:12"/>and the nimbleſt Crafts-men: Theſe are the Men that maintain <hi>Monarchy</hi> to be no more <hi>jure divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no,</hi> than <hi>Religion</hi> it ſelf is; that know no ſuch thing as <hi>Paternal,</hi> or <hi>Patriarchal</hi> Monarchy; but ſeem to hold <hi>Common-wealths</hi> to have been <hi>ab Aeterno,</hi> as well as the <hi>World;</hi> and produc't from the <hi>fortuitous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe</hi> of <hi>States-men,</hi> as the other from that of <hi>Atoms:</hi> Theſe are the Men that wrangle loudeſt againſt the <hi>Prerogative</hi> of their <hi>Prince;</hi> and magnifie the power of the <hi>People,</hi> the great <hi>Leviathan.</hi> Theſe diſpute, and deny the right of <hi>Succeſſion,</hi> and make all concerns, all obligations, whether to God or the Laws, ſubmit and bow to their only God, and great <hi>Idol,</hi> Intereſt, or Self-preſervation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Lying,</hi> and <hi>Treachery,</hi> and <hi>cuſtomary Swearing:</hi> Theſe things do qualifie, and diſpoſe a Man to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwear himſelf upon any convenience, or temptation: Becauſe hereby Men throw off that reverence and reſpect to Religion, that fear of Gods Power and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, which would reſtrain them: They have made bold with God's Name ſo often, and by degrees are grown ſo familiar with Him, by calling upon Him in common Converſation; that 'tis no great <hi>strain</hi> to Conſcience, if they make ſome further uſe of Him in their ſerious affairs, and in matters of greater mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. By the cuſtom of <hi>Lying</hi> they have got the knack to deceive, betray and abuſe their Neighbour or Friend; and by the cuſtom of vain and wanton <hi>Swearing,</hi> they have learn't to make nothing of an Oath: Put theſe together, and that is ſoon done, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any occaſion; and then comes forth and commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces a compleat and accompliſh't <hi>Perjurer.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:60755:12"/>
            <p>To this I may add a <hi>readineſs,</hi> and <hi>eaſineſs</hi> to take <hi>new</hi> and <hi>contrary</hi> Oaths: This doth both argue and infer a ſleight eſteem of the obligation of our <hi>former</hi> promiſes and does certainly engage us in <hi>Perjury.</hi> For when Men find themſelves entangled, by different, and contradictory Oaths; we may preſume by their actions, that they thus argue with themſelves; Since we have taken ſeveral, and <hi>croſs</hi> Oaths; it is at leaſt in our liberty to be oblig'd by whether we pleaſe; or rather, the laſt ought to take place and juſtle out the former, as being more ſuitable to our ſecond and beſt thoughts, and more uſeful to our preſent deſigns. And ſo <hi>Peccant &amp; jurando &amp; juramentum ſervando,</hi> they add ſin to ſin; they ſin both by taking, and by keeping their Oath; whereas they ought in theſe circumſtances to obſerve the Rules of the Caſuiſts: <hi>In malis promiſſis reſcinde fidem: in turpi voto, muta decretum; quod incautè voviſti, non facias: impia est promiſſio, quae ſcelere adimpletur:</hi>
               <note place="margin">In lib. de ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cialib. Legib.</note> Or as <hi>Philo</hi> directs them, <hi>To abſtain from their unjuſt and miſchievous pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes, notwithstanding their Oath, and to implore God's pardon for their raſh, and ſinful ſwearing; to diſcard their falſe Oath, and adhere to their known duty, and the commands of God; for to double your guilt, when you may come off, and be eas'd of the half, is a piece of madneſs and frenſie almoſt incurable,</hi> ſays <hi>He.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To theſe I might add the uſual <hi>occaſions,</hi> and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>temptations</hi> to this ſin: Such are</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Poverty</hi> and <hi>Neceſſity; Covetouſneſs,</hi> and <hi>hope of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward;</hi> as alſo <hi>Fear</hi> whether of <hi>Shame</hi> or of <hi>Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> or of <hi>Both:</hi> In ſome <hi>Ambition</hi> and <hi>Popularity,</hi> a deſire, and thirſt after honour and greatneſs. In <hi>others,</hi> or perhaps in the <hi>ſame, Revenge</hi> and <hi>Malice;</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:60755:13"/>or elſe <hi>Favour, Affection</hi> and <hi>Partiality:</hi> Or laſtly, <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, Sedition</hi> and <hi>Deſigns</hi> againſt the <hi>Government.</hi> As to <hi>All</hi> which, it may be enough to remark, that when theſe furious <hi>paſſions,</hi> and violent <hi>deſires</hi> are able to over-Maſter, and run down the fear of God, and the reverence of an Oath in the hearts of Men; then is Perjury the moſt eaſie and compendious, the moſt ſecure, the moſt proper way to <hi>relieve</hi> their <hi>wants,</hi> or <hi>ſatisfie</hi> their <hi>covetous</hi> deſires, or to <hi>rid</hi> them of their <hi>fears,</hi> or to <hi>gratifie</hi> their <hi>ambition,</hi> or to <hi>pleaſure</hi> their <hi>Friends,</hi> or <hi>diſpatch</hi> their <hi>Enemies,</hi> or to <hi>compaſs</hi> and <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat</hi> their <hi>Seditious deſigns.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this ſhall ſuffice to have ſpoken to the Third, becauſe I haſten to the Fourth, and Laſt Head of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Puniſhments of Perjury: and theſe are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere and dreadful in proportion to the guilt of this great ſin. It is a good Rule: <hi>Semper perpendendum eſt damnum, quod ex perjurio reſultat:</hi> Men ought to weigh well the damages and miſchievous conſequences of their falſe-witneſſing and perfidiouſneſs (not to others only, but) to themſelves; that if Conſcience, and the Senſe of their duty cannot prevail with them, they may be reſtrain'd by the fear of ſuffering.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl'us.</hi> 7.36.</note> 
               <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the end</hi> (ſays a Wiſe Man) <hi>and Thou ſhalt never do amiſs.</hi> See what will come on't; ſee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Perjury will quit coſt, and turn to account; and then venture upon it; if you think t'will prove for your advantage.</p>
            <p>Severe Judgments are denounc't againſt this ſin by the <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man:</hi> God declares, that <hi>He
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:60755:13"/>will not hold him guiltleſs, that taketh His Name in vain,</hi> or <hi>forſwears himſelf,</hi> as our <hi>Saviour</hi> expounds it.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.33.</note> He will not pardon him; He will not leave him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puniſh't;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ainſworth</hi> on <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.7.</note> He will not hold him juſt or innocent in the great Day of Judgement. By the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> a <hi>Falſe-witneſs</hi> was to ſuffer the <hi>ſame</hi> thing as a <hi>puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut</hi> 19.19.</note> that he <hi>intended</hi> to have brought upon his <hi>Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> as a <hi>miſchief.</hi> And God declares the ſeverity of his Judgments againſt this ſin by the Prophet <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariah:</hi> The <hi>flying Roll</hi> was an Emblem of the <hi>Curſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 5.3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>that goeth forth over the face of the whole Earth, and ſhall enter into the Houſe of him, That ſweareth falſly by my Name, and it ſhall remain in the midst of his Houſe, and ſhall conſume it with the Timber there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and the Stones thereof;</hi> it ſhall <hi>entail</hi> a Curſe upon his <hi>Family,</hi> and <hi>Estate;</hi> as it is commonly expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
            <p>As to the Puniſhments denounc't againſt this ſin by the Laws of Men: I ſhall not preſume to recount what the <hi>Common Law</hi> does inflict upon Perſons con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vict of Perjury: But what ſome <hi>Canons</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> and the <hi>Civil Laws</hi> define, I ſhall declare briefly. A Perjurer ſhall be <hi>Ten</hi> years Excommunicate, ſays <hi>S. Baſil. They that Subborn others to forſwear themſelves,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Can.</hi> 64.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall not be received into Communion till the point of death; and thoſe, that are drawn in, ſhall for ever af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be depriv'd of the priviledge of giving in their Teſtimony in any caſe, and according to Law, branded with infamy:</hi> ſays the Council of <hi>Maſcon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tom.</hi> 5. p. 970. <hi>Can.</hi> 17.</note> 
               <hi>Shall never be deem'd worthy to take an Oath; nor to lye in hallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ground:</hi> That is, ſhall be deny'd Chriſtian Burial, <hi>ſays another.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:60755:14"/>
            <p>And a <hi>Council</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> here in the year One Thouſand and Nine, call'd <hi>Concilium Aenhamenſe,</hi> ranks 'em with <hi>Witches, Sorcerers, Necromancers, egregious Strumpets,</hi> &amp;c. And Decrees thus againſt 'em: <hi>Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam terrâ indignos, è terrâ projicite, ut purior ſit deinceps populus;</hi> as unworthy to enjoy the priviledge and benefit of their Native Countrey; <hi>Turn</hi> them out, and <hi>Baniſh</hi> 'em, that the <hi>Land</hi> may be cleanſed, and the reſt preſerved from the <hi>infection.</hi> If this <hi>good Engliſh Cannon</hi> were now in force; if this courſe were taken with thoſe, that are notoriouſly guilty of this Crime; we might have a fair riddance of the perfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious diſturbers of our Peace and Government; we might have a juſt hope to ſee the reſt of our people (who are drawn in by examples, or abuſed by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders) to return to their Wits and their Honeſty again, to their former ſettlement and quiet, to their Callings and proper buſineſs; who now ſpend their time, and trouble their heads about <hi>News</hi> and <hi>Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks:</hi> We might hope to ſee an end of thoſe jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, thoſe Murmurings and clamours, thoſe Factious and Seditious deſigns, and Practices, that have put our people into ſuch a fermentation, and <hi>Paroxyſm,</hi> ſo high a fit of <hi>Frenſie,</hi> that they are grown frantick, and delirous, do rave and talk idly, and look wildly, and act extravagantly, do miſchief to themſelves and others, and threat'n to lay violent hands on the Laws, and the Government. But to proceed.</p>
            <p>Perjury by the <hi>Civil Law</hi> is puniſhable by <hi>Baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> or <hi>Scourging,</hi> and always with <hi>Infamy</hi> beſide. But if a Man <hi>loſt his Life</hi> by the Perjury, as by <hi>falſe-wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> in <hi>Capital Caſes,</hi> then it was puniſh't by <hi>Death, Manum perdant perjuri.</hi> Let them <hi>loſe their hand,</hi> ſays
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:60755:14"/>
               <hi>Charles the Great:</hi> the right hand, the ſame that was laid on the Goſpels, at taking the Oath. But what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the <hi>Laws of Men</hi> define in this caſe, I am ſure, nothing can be ſo ſevere, ſo dreadful, as what we bring upon our ſelves, and call upon God to inflict upon us, when we ſwear falſly: For every Oath doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude an <hi>Execration,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Plutarch.</hi>
               </note> or <hi>Curſe</hi> upon our ſelves in caſe of <hi>Perjury;</hi> and that, whether the Curſe be formally expreſs'd, or only imply'd: For who ever appeals to God, as a Witneſs of the ſincerity of his heart, and the truth of his words, doth thereby alſo invoke Him, as the Judge, and Avenger of his Perjury, and Perfidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, in caſe he do forſwear himſelf. This would appear more clearly upon the view of ſeveral Ancient Forms of Swearing, that have an expreſs Curſe annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them: Examples whereof may be found in abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, collected by <hi>Briſſonius, Fileſacus,</hi> and others.</p>
            <p>The uſual Form among us that (as it were) <hi>binds</hi> the Oath, and makes the <hi>Sanction</hi> is This:
<note place="margin">Lib. VIII. <hi>Select.</hi> lib. 3.</note> 
               <hi>So help me God;</hi> in direct Invocation: Or <hi>So help you God,</hi> in Adjuration. Which contains and implyes a moſt dreadful Imprecation, a horrible <hi>Curſe</hi> upon our own Souls, if we Swear falſly; for we then call upon God, to withdraw his <hi>Help,</hi> his <hi>Grace,</hi> his <hi>Mercy</hi> from us; we utterly forfeit his favour, and devote our ſelves to his ſevereſt Vengeance. Every Man, that takes an Oath, doth in effect addreſs himſelf to God, at this rate: As far forth, as I <hi>depoſe,</hi> or <hi>promiſe truly</hi> or <hi>faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully;</hi> ſo do Thou <hi>Help</hi> me (O God I beſeech Thee) and <hi>bleſs</hi> me, <hi>protect</hi> and <hi>proſper</hi> me: But if I <hi>Swear falſly,</hi> if I <hi>Teſtifie a lye,</hi> if I <hi>Promiſe deceitfully,</hi> if I prove <hi>Treacherous</hi> to my word; then <hi>O God,</hi> Thou Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Judge, Thou God of Vengeance, I diſclaim, and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:60755:15"/>renounce all <hi>help,</hi> all <hi>hopes</hi> of mercy from Thee: Let Thy <hi>Vengeance</hi> purſue, and haunt me; Let all the <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> of Thy wrath ſeiſe and fall upon me: May'ſt Thou never <hi>help</hi> me, nor incline Thy <hi>mercy</hi> toward me, but <hi>caſt me away in Thy diſpleaſure,</hi> and ſuffer me to <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh</hi> both here and hereafter.</p>
            <p>Oh! What a load muſt this be to the <hi>Perjurer</hi>'s <hi>Conſcience?</hi> What can the <hi>World</hi> afford, that is able to relieve or ſupport a Soul ſo <hi>deſperately</hi> guilty, ſo <hi>mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally</hi> wounded? To whom ſhall he flee for ſuccour, when <hi>God</hi> has forſaken him, and all good Men <hi>abhor</hi> him, and his own Conſcience doth <hi>gripe</hi> and <hi>tear</hi> him? And what will it be in the end thereof? What ſhall be the fatal Doom of the <hi>Perjur'd,</hi> but Eternal ruine, and damnation? His portion ſhall be with the <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite,</hi> and with the <hi>Traytor,</hi> with <hi>Achitophel</hi> and <hi>Judas:</hi> Don't think, becauſe God does not lay them ſprawl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with a <hi>Thunder-bolt,</hi> or ſtrike him over the Face with a flaſh of <hi>Light'ning,</hi> that therefore he is ſafe, and ſhall eſcape the vengeance of the <hi>Almighty:</hi> No ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly;
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Phil. deſpecial. Leg.</hi>
               </note> though God doth ſuſpend the Execution, He will one day reckon with, and take account of this wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and unfaithful Servant: <hi>He will not be merciful to them, that offend thus out of malicious wickedneſs, but leaves 'em often in an incorrigible eſtate,</hi> and <hi>rare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> vouchſafes 'em the grace of Repentance, and indeed <hi>They deſerve no better,</hi> ſays <hi>Philo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If <hi>Their</hi> caſe then be ſo dangerous, and almoſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate, is it not ſad to obſerve ſo many Thouſands involved in this great guilt, hugging themſelves in the poſſeſſion, and enjoyment of the advantages of their Perjury, and never expreſſing any reſentment
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:60755:15"/>and remorſe, for having taken their unlawful and impious <hi>Oaths,</hi> and for having acted by virtue of <hi>them,</hi> the greateſt Villanies. What! though the <hi>Act of Oblivion</hi> hath exempted 'em from the <hi>penalties</hi> of the <hi>Law?</hi> but can it ſecure 'em from the <hi>judgments</hi> of God? That hath <hi>ſav'd their lives;</hi> but can it <hi>purge their Conſciences,</hi> and <hi>ſave their Souls</hi> too? What, though they have (ſome of them) <hi>renounc't</hi> the obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, that was for their <hi>advantage?</hi> That <hi>alone</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not demonſtrate their hearty ſorrow and Repentance. Have they <hi>mourn'd,</hi> and <hi>bewail'd,</hi> and <hi>confeſs'd</hi> their ſin? Have they begg'd <hi>God</hi>'s, and the <hi>King</hi>'s par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don? Have they given <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> to the <hi>Church</hi> for the <hi>ſcandal?</hi> Have they made <hi>reſtitution</hi> of the <hi>Spoil,</hi> the <hi>Plunder,</hi> and the <hi>Rapine,</hi> the <hi>Murther,</hi> and the <hi>Sacriledge?</hi> Have they given <hi>Security</hi> for their peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and <hi>good Behaviour</hi> for the <hi>future?</hi> I have ſo much <hi>Charity</hi> to wiſh it were ſo, with all my Soul; but I have not <hi>Faith</hi> to believe it: For do they not retain many of them, their <hi>old Principles?</hi> Do they not train up their <hi>Pupils</hi> in their <hi>own way,</hi> in their <hi>old Diſcipline?</hi> Are they not <hi>practiſing</hi> over again their <hi>former Methods?</hi> Are they not ready for a <hi>new Oath,</hi> as bad, or <hi>worſe</hi> than the <hi>former?</hi> Is not the <hi>fatal Compoſition</hi> prepared? And are they not <hi>Dieted</hi> and fitly diſpos'd to <hi>take</hi> it? How is it poſſible to reconcile theſe things with any ſhew of Repentance, or pretence of Loyalty? What milder, and more gentle thought ſoever, others may have, I know not; but I declare that I could not adminiſter one drop of comfort from the <hi>promiſes</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> to a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jur'd Soul; though he ſhould ſeem never ſo ſenſible of his ſin and danger, unleſs I could prevail with him to <hi>diſgorge</hi> the envenom'd <hi>Morſel,</hi> to make <hi>ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:60755:16"/>to the <hi>injur'd</hi> party, if poſſible, and teſtifie the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity of his Repentance by <hi>Reſtitution.</hi> There is mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy with God for the truly Penitent; but the caſe of the <hi>Perjurer</hi> is dangerous and difficult; His Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance muſt be <hi>ſevere,</hi> and <hi>very particular;</hi> it will coſt him abundance of Tears to waſh off ſo foul a ſtain; his <hi>Contrition</hi> muſt be <hi>ſharp</hi> and <hi>violent,</hi> in proportion to the guilt and aggravations of <hi>this</hi> ſin.</p>
            <p>I have done with the parts of the Text: And now if any <hi>Factious,</hi> and <hi>ill-minded</hi> Perſons ſhall take upon them to quarrel and clamour at this honeſt and well-intended Diſcourſe; I will aſſure 'em, that I ſhall be ſo far from being troubled, or diſcourag'd by their <hi>Cenſure,</hi> that I ſhall take it for a kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and great commendation; I ſhall look upon it as an argument of their <hi>Conviction,</hi> and the ſenſe of their <hi>Guilt;</hi> which may prove, by God's grace, the <hi>firſt ſtep</hi> toward their <hi>late</hi> Repentance. Beſide, if they are not <hi>guilty</hi> of Perjury themſelves, or <hi>favourers</hi> of them that are, Why are they <hi>concern'd?</hi> Who hath <hi>meddled</hi> with 'em, or <hi>touch't</hi> 'em? But if they are, it is fit they be <hi>told</hi> of it, to ſome purpoſe; that they may be ſenſible of their guilt and danger, that they may Repent of their ſin, and continue no longer in it;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.13.</note> that <hi>They may hear, and fear, and do no more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuouſly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I Conclude with a two-fold Exhortation: The one to thoſe, that may be concern'd either as <hi>Witneſſes,</hi> or <hi>Jurors:</hi> The other in general to All that are <hi>faithful and truly Loyal to their Prince.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:60755:16"/>
            <p>As to the firſt, I do moſt earneſtly exhort and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech <hi>Them</hi> to conſider the <hi>nature and ſeveral kinds,</hi> the <hi>heinouſneſs,</hi> the <hi>occaſions</hi> and the <hi>puniſhments</hi> of <hi>this ſin;</hi> and to take eſpecial care ſo to diſcharge and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have themſelves, as that they may not in <hi>any kind,</hi> upon <hi>any account</hi> incur the guilt of it: To this end I would beg of them, and adviſe them two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. When they are call'd to <hi>take</hi> their <hi>Oaths,</hi> to <hi>do</hi> it with all <hi>reverence:</hi> And</p>
            <p n="2">2. To obſerve, and act according to <hi>them,</hi> with a good Conſcience. They are to conſider, that an Oath is a <hi>Sacred</hi> and <hi>Solemn Act</hi> of <hi>Religion,</hi> and <hi>Divine Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip;</hi> and ought to be perform'd with as much <hi>Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, fixedneſs of Intention,</hi> and <hi>Fervency,</hi> with as much <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Humility</hi> as any other part of God's Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. And therefore it were to be wiſh't, that the Oaths in our <hi>Courts</hi> were adminiſtred with more <hi>Leiſure</hi> and <hi>Gravity,</hi> with more <hi>State</hi> and <hi>Solemnity,</hi> with more <hi>Emphatical Rites</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> than are commonly uſed; to ſtrike an awe, and terrour into the minds of our <hi>People,</hi> and make them more <hi>ſerious</hi> and <hi>atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive;</hi> or at leaſt, that <hi>They</hi> were conſtantly admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh't to compoſe themſelves into a <hi>Religious temper</hi> of mind, when they come to <hi>Swear;</hi> and alſo were fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently advis'd to remember the <hi>Tenour</hi> or <hi>Purport</hi> of their <hi>Oaths.</hi> For (I fear) our People, eſpecially the meaner ſort, are apt to be <hi>amus'd</hi> and <hi>abaſh't,</hi> when they are call'd into the <hi>Court,</hi> and appear in that <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Aſſembly:</hi> They cannot eaſily recollect themſelves, and take off their thoughts from the variety of <hi>ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing objects;</hi> or they are <hi>framing</hi> their Evidence into <hi>method;</hi> or <hi>dreſſing</hi> up their teſtimony in <hi>fine</hi> words,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:60755:17"/>and <hi>handſome phraſes;</hi> or thinking of any thing ſooner, than what they ſhould do.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I do adviſe, and exhort them to <hi>obſerve their Oaths,</hi> carefully to <hi>ſpeak</hi> and <hi>act,</hi> according to the tenour and obligation of them: <hi>To ſet God before their Eyes,</hi> and a <hi>Watch before the door of their Lips,</hi> and to <hi>place his Fear in their hearts;</hi> To give in their <hi>Teſtimony,</hi> or their <hi>Verdict,</hi> not out of <hi>Love</hi> or <hi>Malice, Fear</hi> or <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour,</hi> or <hi>hope of Reward,</hi> &amp;c. but out of <hi>Conſcience</hi> and full <hi>Conviction,</hi> and with a ſincere <hi>reſpect</hi> to truth and juſtice.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To All, that are <hi>Faithful</hi> and <hi>Loyal</hi> to their <hi>Prince,</hi> I apply the advice of <hi>Solomon:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſiaſt.</hi> 8.2.</note> 
               <hi>I counſel you to keep the King's Commandment, and that in regard of the Oath of God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 30.2.</note> By this your <hi>Souls</hi> are <hi>bound with a Bond,</hi> as God ſpeaks: your hearts are knit to your <hi>Soveraign</hi> in <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Allegiance:</hi> No power on Earth can <hi>diſpenſe</hi> with your Oath; No <hi>pretence</hi> can <hi>juſtifie</hi> the <hi>breach</hi> of your promiſe, and ſworn duty; You <hi>cannot,</hi> you <hi>must not</hi> go from your word, upon any account whatever.</p>
            <p>Let <hi>us</hi> therefore be as careful to <hi>keep</hi> our Oaths, as the Factious deſigners are to <hi>break</hi> them. Let us be as zealous and couragious and induſtrious too, to <hi>ſupport,</hi> and preſerve the Government both in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> as they are ſtubbornly bent, and furiouſly acted to <hi>demoliſh</hi> and <hi>deſtroy</hi> it: While we have good <hi>Laws,</hi> for God's ſake, let us <hi>live</hi> and <hi>act</hi> according to them; and let <hi>them</hi> have their <hi>courſe</hi> upon <hi>All</hi> thoſe, that do <hi>vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, affront,</hi> and <hi>defie them:</hi> Thoſe that pretend to <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain</hi> of <hi>Arbitrary power,</hi> they, methinks, ought to have <hi>Law</hi> enough, their belly full, that they may complain for ſomething; if they deſerve it.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:60755:17"/>
            <p>It is recorded of that ſtiff-neck't,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Judges</hi> 11.7.10, 11.</note> and murmuring people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that <hi>They ſerv'd the Lord all the days of</hi> Joſhua, <hi>and all the days of the Elders, that out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liv'd</hi> Joſhua, <hi>who had ſeen all the great works of the Lord, that he had done for</hi> Iſrael; though the <hi>next generation that knew not the Lord, nor the works, that He had done</hi> for their Fathers, <hi>forſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k the Lord, and ſerv'd</hi> Baal <hi>and</hi> Aſhtaroth. Let <hi>us</hi> then, for God's ſake, be as ingenuous, and grateful, at leaſt, as <hi>They</hi> were: Let <hi>us</hi> that have ſeen all the great works of the <hi>Lord,</hi> in his wonderful deliverance from our <hi>Aegyptian</hi> bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, in the miraculous Reſtauration of our <hi>Soveraign</hi> and <hi>Religion:</hi> Let <hi>us</hi> ſerve the <hi>Lord</hi> and the <hi>King</hi> too, all the days of <hi>our</hi> lives, and not be ſo fooliſhly mad, and ſo deſperately wicked, as to relapſe, and return to our former <hi>frenſy</hi> in <hi>this</hi> Age. Methinks <hi>one Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> were ſufficient for <hi>one Generation;</hi> and it were <hi>too much</hi> to be <hi>twice</hi> chous'd by the <hi>ſame-Men,</hi> upon the <hi>ſame Pretences,</hi> by the <hi>ſame Artifices,</hi> and <hi>Methods:</hi> We were not uſed ſo <hi>kindly</hi> by our late <hi>Taskmaſters,</hi> as to be ſond and dote upon a <hi>ſecond Slavery:</hi> The <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility,</hi> the <hi>Gentry,</hi> the <hi>Freeholders</hi> in general may <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member</hi> how much they <hi>ſuffered</hi> reſpectively, in their <hi>Honcurs</hi> or <hi>Eſtates,</hi> in their <hi>Liberties</hi> and <hi>Properties,</hi> by <hi>Popular fury,</hi> and <hi>Military inſolence;</hi> and therefore ought to <hi>look forward</hi> too, and conſider, what they muſt expect, if the <hi>Faction</hi> ſhould prevail, if the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy</hi> be deſtroy'd, if the <hi>worſt</hi> of our <hi>fellow Subiects</hi> ſhould once more <hi>enſlave</hi> us.</p>
            <p>It highly concerns us <hi>All</hi> therefore, both in <hi>Duty</hi> and <hi>Intereſt,</hi> to continue ſirmly Loyal to the <hi>King,</hi> and true to the <hi>Monarchy;</hi> to keep our <hi>old, lawful Oaths,</hi> and to <hi>abhor</hi> all <hi>illegal</hi> and <hi>new</hi> ones; to be honeſt
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:60755:18"/>and faithful, and peaceable and obedient to the <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi> It is ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Duty, to beg of God to preſerve us from <hi>Wicked</hi> and <hi>Deceitful</hi> Men, from the <hi>Perfidious,</hi> and the <hi>Perjur'd,</hi> from <hi>bare</hi> Pretenders to <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Reformation,</hi> from <hi>falſe</hi> Friends, and <hi>falſe</hi> Brethren; to beg of God to preſerve our <hi>King</hi> in Peace and fafety, the <hi>Monarchy</hi> in its full ſtrength, and juſt rights, the <hi>Church</hi> in purity, and the <hi>Laws</hi> in vigour and due exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution.</p>
            <p>And let <hi>All,</hi> that wiſh well to our <hi>Sion,</hi> ſay <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:60755:18"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
